
<tei><text><body><head>COMMENTARY</head><p>
    <pb n="149"/>
    <app><lem xml:lang="grc">τῶν εἰδῶν αὐτῆς</lem></app>
The εἴδη meant are epic poetry, Tragedy, and 
Comedy, as is clear from 6, 1449 b 21, where the main subjects for
consideration in the Poetics are enumerated. Lyric poetry, apart
from an occasional reference to the Dithyramb and Nome, or the
chorica in Tragedy, is ignored in the existing Poetics ; and there
is little or no reason to suppose it to have been discussed in
the lost portion of the book. The probability is that, from the
importance of its musical element, it belonged in Aristotle’s
classification of the arts to the theory of μελοποιία rather than to
that of poetry proper. The work of the two lyric poets Phrynis
and Timotheus is put under the head of μελοποιία in Metaph. a 1,
993 15; and in the Problems, where Phrynichus is said to have
been a μελοποιός rather than a tragedian (Probl. 18. 31, 920 211
Διὰ τί οἱ περὶ Φρύνιχον ἦσαν μᾶλλον μελοποιοί ; ἢ διὰ τὸ πολλαπλά-
σια εἶναι τότε τὰ μέλη ἐν ταῖς τραγῳδίαις τῶν μέτρων ;), the same view
is implied of the lyric parts of Tragedy. It is to be remembered
too that Aristophanes in Ran. 1250 makes Euripides begin his
criticism of the chorica in Aeschylus by calling him a κακὸς
μελοποιός.
</p><p>
For the antithesis in the text comp. 26, 1462b 16 καὶ αὐτῶν καὶ
τῶν εἰδῶν.—Top. 1. 15, 106 b 37 ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ ἐπὶ τῶν ἄλλων [scil.
ὀνομάτων], ὅταν αὐτὸ πλεοναχῶς λέγηται, καὶ ἡ πτῶσις ἡ ἀπ᾽ αὐτοῦ
πλεοναχῶς ῥηθήσεται, καὶ εἰ ἡ πτῶσις, καὶ αὐτό.—Eth. E. 7. 15;
1248 b 22 δικαιοσύνη καὶ αὐτὴ καὶ αἱ πράξεις.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἣν τινα δύναμιν ἕκαστον ἔχει</lem></app>
= ὅ τι δύναται ἕκαστον : comp. Pol.
5. 2, 1302 b 5 τούτων δὲ ὕβρις μὲν καὶ κέρδος τίνα ἔχουσι δύναμιν καὶ
πῶς αἴτια, σχεδόν ἐστι φανερόν ... δῆλον δὲ καὶ ἡ τιμὴ καὶ τί δύναται
καὶ πῶς αἰτία στάσεως. Each species of poetry has its special
capacities, which enable it to do what the rest either cannot do at
all or cannot do so well and effectively. Other Aristotelian in-
stances of δύναμις with a sense approximating to our ‘ function’ or
‘effect ’ will be found in Bon. Ind. 206 b 29.</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">συνίστασθαι</lem></app><milestone n="a9"/>
 is a passive in 26, 1462a16, and probably also in 
24,1460a 28. That it is a passive in the present passage is shown

<pb n="98"/>



1447 a 9 
by the parallels, τοὺς συνεστῶτας εὖ μύθους in 7, 145b32, and
οὕτω συνεστάναι τὸν μῦθον in 14, 1453 b 4.
</p>

<p>a10
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">καλῶς ἕξειν</lem></app>: 13,1453 212 τὸν καλῶς ἔχοντα μῦθον.---24, 1459 b 12
τὰς διανοίας καὶ τὴν λέξιν ἔχειν καλῶς. As anything good of its
kind may be said to be καλόν, so anything that is in the condition
in which it ought to be is said to καλῶς ἔχειν (comp. Bon. Ind.
360 b 38).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἔτι δὲ ἐκ πόσων καὶ ποίων ἐστὶ μορίων</lem></app>, scil. ἡ ποίησις. Many of
the translators, however, suppose the subject to be ἕκαστον εἶδος
(‘ex quot et cujusmodi partibus constent singulae species,’ Goulston).
The question is considered in chap. 6 in reference to Tragedy,
and in 24, 1450b τὸ in reference to epic poetry.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">περὶ τῶν ἄλλων ὅσα τῆς αὐτῆς ἐστι μεθόδου</lem></app>: Soph. el. 33, 183 b 12
δεδήλωται δὲ καὶ περὶ τῶν ἄλλων ὅσα τῆς αὐτῆς μεθόδου τῶν λόγων
ἐστίν. The meaning οἵ μέθοδος, a favourite word with Aristotle,
has been discussed by Waitz, Org. 2 p. 297 (comp. Bon. Ind.
449 b 43). 
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">λέγωμεν ἀρξάμενοι κτἑ</lem></app>, The language here is very like that in
Soph. el. 1, 164a 20 περὶ δὲ τῶν σοφιστικῶν ἐλέγχων . . . λέγωμεν
ἀρξάμενοι κατὰ φύσιν ἀπὸ τῶν πρώτων (comp. De sensu 1, 436 a 6;
De part. an. 1.5, 646a3; 2.10,655b28; Eth. E. 1.7, 1217 a 10;
Rhet. τ. 13, 13731). In order to determine the definition
of poetry, or rather of Tragedy as the highest form of the art,
Aristotle starts with the assumption that Tragedy, together with
certain other allied arts, comes under the general head of μίμησις,
‘imitation,’ and then proceeds by successive divisions of this genus
to note one by one the various points which differentiate it from
the rest. (1) Tragedy has language, metre, and music as its
means of imitation ; the music in it, however, comes in only from
time to time, in the choral parts—which distinguishes it from the
Nome and the Dithyramb. (2) It represents noble personages—
which distinguishes it from Comedy. (3) It has a dramatic form—
which distinguishes it from the Epic. These with other differentiae
less clearly accounted for are combined in the definition of Tragedy
at the opening of chap. 6. The logical order here exemplified is
what Aristotle regards as the natural order of procedure: Phys.
1. 7, 189 b 31 ἔστι γὰρ κατὰ φύσιν τὰ κοινὰ πρῶτον εἰπόντας οὕτω τὰ
περὶ ἕκαστον ἴδια θεωρεῖν. 
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἐποποιία κτἑ.</lem></app> This enumeration of imitative arts comprises the 
four great species of poetry distinguished by Plato in Rep. 394 c, 
together with two purely musical arts, αὐλητική and κιθαριστική

<pb n="99"/>


These last may be supposed to be added partly on account of the 1447  a 13
manifest analogy between them and poetry, both being imitative
arts appealing to the ear, and partly also on account of the historical connexion of poetry with music (comp. Cicero De Orat. 3,174
musici, qui erant quondam idem poetae). Even Plato occasionally
merges the one in the other. In the Republic μουσική includes
poetry, and in Symp. 205 c poetry includes τὸ περὶ τὴν μουσικήν.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἡ τῆς τραγῳδίας ποίησις</lem></app>: b 26 ἡ τῶν διθυραμβικῶν ποίησις.---
Plato Gorg. 501 Ε ἡ τῶν διθυράμβων ποίησις.---- 502 Β ἡ τῆς τραγῳδίας ποίησις.

a14
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">διθυραμβοποιητικὴ</lem></app>. Plato cites the Dithyramb as an instance of 
the non-imitative type of poetry: Rep. 394 ὁ τῆς ποιήσεως... ἡ
μὲν διὰ μιμήσεως ὅλη ἐστίν, ὥσπερ σὺ λέγεις, τραγῳδία τε καὶ κωμῳδία,
ἡ δὲ δι᾽ ἀπαγγελίας αὐτοῦ τοῦ ποιητοῦ--- εὕροις δ᾽ ἂν αὐτὴν μάλιστά
που ἐν διθυράμβοις. By Aristotle’s time, however, the Dithyramb
(as also the Nome) had lost its original form, and become
‘imitative ’ or semi-dramatic, a sort of musical counterpart of the
Drama, dealing with the same kinds of subject as Tragedy, and
with solos by professional singers corresponding to the speeches of
the tragic actors. This change in the character of the Dithyramb
is noted in Probl. 19. 15, 918 b 18 οἱ διθύραμβοι, ἐπειδὴ μιμητικοὶ
ἐγένοντο, οὐκέτι ἔχουσιν ἀντιστρόφους, πρότερον δὲ εἶχον: αἴτιον δὲ ὅτι
τὸ παλαιὸν οἱ ἐλεύθεροι ἐχόρευον αὐτοί πολλοὺς οὖν ἀγωνιστικῶς
ἄδειν χαλεπὸν ἦν, ὥστε ἐναρμόνια μέλη ἐνῇδον: μεταβάλλειν γὰρ
πολλὰς μεταβολὰς τῷ ἑνὶ ῥᾷον ἢ τοῖς πολλοῖς, καὶ τῷ ἀγωνιστῇ
ἢ τοῖς τὸ ἦθος φυλάττουσιν (comp. Bergk, Gr. Litt. 2 p. 529, and
Wilamowitz, Euripides Herakles1 p. 79). In this mention of the
Dithyramb, therefore, Aristotle does not cite it as a type of lyric
poetry in general (as is often supposed), but as representing an
imitative or dramatic form of lyric—a lyrical μίμησις or picture of
life and manners. A certain approximation to this later form of
Dithyramb is to be seen in Bacchylides (Comparetti, Mélanges
Weil p. 30).

a15
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τῆς αὐλητικῆς ἡ πλείστη</lem></app> : De Caelo 3. 1, 298 b 2 τὴν πλείστην 
τῆς περὶ φύσεως ἱστορίας (comp. Kühner, Gr. Gr 2. 1 p. 279).
The αὐλός was the accompaniment of the Dithyramb and the κιθάρα
of the Nome. That, however, is not the reason for this reference
to them, as it is clear from a23 that Aristotle is thinking rather of
music without words, i.e. of that which was termed in antiquity ψιλὴ
αὔλησις and ψιλὴ κιθάρισις. Plato in the Laws (669 E) sets his face
against this purely instrumental music, which had evidently attained

<pb n="100"/>



to a high degree of perfection in his time, on the ground that it
ends in a mere display of technical execution (θαυματουργία) and
a ‘brutish noise’ (φωνῆς θηριώδους σφόδρα φίλον)  Aristotle’s
language in Pol. 8. 6, 1341 a 11 τὰ θαυμάσια καὶ περιττὰ τῶν ἔργων
ἃ νῦν ἐλήλυθεν εἰς τοὺς ἀγῶνας, seems to imply that there was in his
view some truth in Plato’s criticism. In the present passage
accordingly, instead of saying ἡ αὐλητική, or ἡ αὐλητικὴ πᾶσα, he
adopts the qualified form of expression, τῆς αὐλητικῆς ἡ πλείστη,
in order to show that he is not unaware of there being exceptions
to the rule.

a16</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">μιμήσεις</lem></app>. The general meaning of μιμεῖσθαι is either ‘to do
what another has done’, or ‘to make something like something
else ’, i.e. to represent by means of a copy or counterfeit of some
sort. The primitive sense of the word must have been ‘to play
the μῖμος,’ to reproduce the language, tones, gestures, etc., of
another—a sense which survives in the use of the term for the
imitation of persons by actors on the stage. In actual use
the word is wide enough to include the counterfeiting of move-
ment and attitude by the dancer, that of voice and sound by the
singer and musician, that of the forms and colours of things by
the sculptor and painter, and even the representation of things in
words, as in speech and literature. A noteworthy variation, how-
ever, is to be observed in the application of the word to a work of
literature. Owing to the traditional associations connected with it
Plato in the Republic opposes μίμησις to narrative, restricting
it to the dramatic mode of statement, in which the speaker effaces
himself, as it were, and identifies himself with his personages:
Rep. 393 B οὐκοῦν διήγησις μέν ἐστι καὶ ὅταν τὰς ῥήσεις ἑκάστοτε λέγῃ
[scil. Ὅμηρος] καὶ ὅταν τὰ μεταξὺ τῶν ῥήσεων; Πῶς γὰρ οὔ; ᾿Αλλ᾽
ὅταν γέ τινα λέγῃ ῥῆσιν ὥς τις ἄλλος ὦν, ἄρ᾽ οὐ τότε ὁμοιοῦν αὐτὸν
φήσομεν ὅτι μάλιστα τὴν αὑτοῦ λέξιν ἑκάστῳ ὃν ἂν προείπῃ ὡς
ἐροῦντα; Φήσομεν: τί γάρ ; Οὐκοῦν τό γε ὁμοιοῦν ἑαυτὸν ἄλλῳ ἢ κατὰ
φωνὴν ἢ κατὰ σχῆμα μιμεῖσθαί ἐστιν ἐκεῖνον ᾧ ἄν τις ὁμοιοῖ; Τί μήν ;
Ἔν δὴ τῷ τοιούτῳ, ὡς ἔοικεν, οὗτός τε καὶ οἱ ἄλλοι ποιηταὶ διὰ
μιμήσεως τὴν διήγησιν ποιοῦνται. Πάνυ μὲν οὖν. εἰ δέ γε μηδαμοῦ
ἑαυτὸν ἀποκρύπτοιτο ὃ ποιητής, πᾶσα ἂν αὐτῷ ἄνευ μιμήσεως ἡ ποίησίς
τε καὶ διήγησις γεγονυῖα εἴη.---304 Β τῆς ποιήσεώς τε καὶ μυθολογίας
ἡ μὲν διὰ μιμήσεως ὅλη ἐστίν, ὥσπερ σὺ λέγεις, τραγῳδία τε καὶ
κωμῳδία, ἡ δὲ δι’ ἀπαγγελίας αὐτοῦ τοῦ ποιητοῦ---εὕροις δ᾽ ἂν αὐτὴν
μάλιστά που ἐν διθυράμβοις--- δ᾽ αὖ ov ἀμφοτέρων ἔν τε τῇ τῶν
ἐπῶν ποιήσει, πολλαχοῦ δὲ καὶ ἄλλοθι. In his use of μιμεῖσθαι in

<pb n="101"/>

the Poetics Aristotle has fallen into a grave inconsistency, as he
distinctly makes it in one place (3, 1448a 21) include narrative,
and in another (24, 1460 a 9) exclude it.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τὸ σύνολον</lem></app>
 qualifies πᾶσαι, what is said of the class as a whole
being opposed to the specific differences which reveal themselves
in it on closer examination; comp. Plato Soph. 220 B BE. τοῦ δὲ
ἐνύδρου [scil. γένους ἡ θήρα] σχεδὸν τὸ σύνολον ἁλιευτική ; ΘΕΑΙ. Ναί,
ΞΕ. Τί δέ; ταύτην αὖ τὴν θήραν ἄρ᾽ οὐκ ἂν κατὰ μέγιστα μέρη δύο
διελοίμην ;
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τῷ γένει ἑτέροις</lem></app>. Forchhammer’s correction τῷ ἐν ἑτέροις is
supposed to be confirmed by the use of the preposition to denote
the means or vehicle of imitation in a 22 and b 29, and also else-
where (3, 1448 a 20 etc.). The sense, however, is just as well
expressed by the simple dative, as it is for instance in the imme-
diate context in a 18 and a 26; and as the means under considera-
tion, λόγος, ἁρμονία, and ῥυθμός, differ in kind, they are rightly
described as γένει ἕτερα. ‘There is no need to restore <add>τῷ</add> γένει ;
Aristotle not unfrequently omits the article in this and cognate
formulas, e.g. in Top. 1. 7, 103213 γένει ταὐτά, in H. A. 2. 1,
497b9 and Metaph. I 10, 1059a14 γένει ἕτεραι In An. post.
2. 15, 988 26-28 we find him saying τῷ γένει and γένει, and in
Eth. N. ro. 5, 1175a25 τῷ εἴδει and εἴδει without perceptible
difference of meaning. The distinction in fact between γένει ἕτερα
and τῷ γένει ἕτερα is not greater than that between ‘different in
kind’ and ‘different in their kind’ in English. A confirmation of
Forchhammer’s reading has been seen in the fact that in
8, 1451 8 17 Ac has τῷ γένει instead of the true reading τῷ ἑνί.
The two cases, however, are not quite parallel ΤΩΓΕΝΕΙ=
ΤΩΙΕΝΙ assumes only a very familiar kind of corruption, whereas
ΤΩΙΕΝΕΙ=ΤΩΙΕΝ leaves an important part of the word (the
termination) unexplained. It is also to be observed that the com-
parison in the next line, ὥσπερ γὰρ καὶ χρώμασι κτἑ., seems to
presuppose γένει ἑτέροις, as χρώματα καὶ σχήματα and φωνή, which
appeal to different senses, are marked instances of things γένει
ἕτερα (comp. An. post. 2. 13, 9734). There is no doubt a
certain inelegance in τῷ γένει ἑτέροις μιμεῖσθαι, but it is not greater
than that in Phys. 1. 7, 191 a 1 διὰ τὸ ἕτερον ὑπάρχειν τὸ εἶναι
αὐτοῖς, or that in Plato Rep. 534 B διαλεκτικὸν καλεῖς τὸν λόγον
ἑκάστου λαμβάνοντα τῆς οὐσίας.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἢ τῷ ἕτερα ἢ τῷ ἑτέρως</lem></app>. The distinction is already in Plato,
Rep. 398 Β ἅ τε γὰρ λεκτἑον καὶ ὡς λεκτἑον εἴρηται.

<pb n="102"/>

καὶ μὴ τὸν αὐτὸν τρόπον. Other instances of parallelismus anti-
theticus will be found in 3, 1448a 22, 6, 1449b 26, 15, 1454 a 30,
24, 1460a 16.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ὥσπερ γὰρ κτἑ</lem></app>. Aristotle prepares us for the difference of means
in these arts by pointing to the difference of means in a larger
group of imitative arts. The distinction between the arts that
address the eye and those that address the ear is frequently noted
by Plato in similar terms, e.g. in Rep. 373 B οἵ τε μιμηταί, πολλοὶ
μὲν οἱ περὶ τὰ σχήματά τε καὶ χρώματα, πολλοὶ δὲ οἱ περὶ μουσικήν,
ποιηταί τε καὶ τούτων ὑπηρέται, ῥαψῳδοὶ ὑποκριταὶ χορευταὶ κτἑ. (comp.
Rep. 603 B; Crat. 423 p; Gorg. 474 E). It is assumed also in
a number of Aristotelian passages (e.g. in An. post. 2. 13, 97b 35;
Eth. N. 3. 13, 1118a3; Pol. 8. 5, 1340a 34). Aristotle has a
special reason for saying ἕτεροι δὲ διὰ τῆς φωνῆς, because the great
imitative capacity of the voice is what renders language and poetry
possible, together with many of the arts subsidiary to the latter:
Rhet. 3. 1, 1404a21 ὑπῆρξε δὲ καὶ ἡ φωνὴ πάντων μιμητικώτατον
τῶν μορίων ἡμῖν: διὸ καὶ αἱ τέχναι συνέστησαν, ἥ τε ῥαψῳδία καὶ ἡ ὑπο-
κριτικὴ καὶ ἄλλαι γε.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">πολλὰ</lem></app>
 is not otiose. The art of the painter or sculptor has
certain limits ; it can represent many things; but there are some
(e.g. character and feeling) that it can only imperfectly or in-
directly express (Pol. 8. 5, 1340a32; comp. Xenophon Mem.
3. 10, 1). The theory in Lessing’s Laocoon is based on an idea
already in Aristotle.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">μιμοῦνταί τινες ἀπεικάζοντες</lem></app> : Xenophon Mem. 3. 10, 1 σώματα
διὰ τῶν χρωμάτων ἀπεικάζοντες ἐκμιμεῖσθε.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">οἱ μὲν διὰ τέχνης οἱ δὲ διὰ συνηθείας</lem></app>
 is thrown in parenthetically,
like the very similar remark in 8, 1451 a 24, ἤτοι διὰ τέχνην ἢ διὰ
φύσιν. As opposed to τέχνη, συνήθεια means much the same
as ἐμπειρία, With which it is coupled in Eth. N. 8. 7, 1158a14
δεῖ δὲ καὶ ἐμπειρίαν λαβεῖν καὶ ἐν συνηθείᾳ γενέσθαι, and in 10. 10,
1181 a 90 οὐ μὴν μικρόν γε ἔοικεν ἡ ἐμπειρία συμβάλλεσθαι· οὐδὲ γὰρ
ἐγίνοντ᾽ ἂν διὰ τῆς πολιτικῆς συνηθείας πολιτικοί. The contrast is
between the skill depending on mere practice or habitude, and
that directed by a consciousness of the rules and principles of the
art which deals with the particular subject. On this distinction
see Metaph. A 1, 980b28, and Mill’s Logic Bk. II. ch. 3 (1,
Ῥ. 214, ed. 4).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἕτεροι δὲ</lem></app>
 corresponds to a foregoing τινές in Eth, N. 1. 1,
1094b 18 ἤδη γὰρ τινες ἀπώλοντο διὰ πλοῦτον, ἕτεροι δὲ δι᾽ ἀνδρείαν.

<pb n="103"/>

Compare also Plato Rep. 349 D μουσικὸν δέ τινα λέγεις, ἕτερον δὲ 
ἄμουσον ;
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">διὰ τῆς φωνῆς</lem></app>
 = τῇ φωνῇ. Aristotle has allowed himself to
repeat the prepositional construction used in the parenthesis. The
emendation of Madius, διὰ τῆς φύσεως, besides making too much
of a merely incidental remark in a parenthesis, leaves χρώμασι καὶ
σχήμασι without an antithesis ; it ignores in fact the whole point of
the analogy to which attention is drawn, the diversity of means.
The diversity of means, λόγος, ῥυθμός, and ἁρμονία, in the group of
imitative arts under consideration is said to be like the diversity of
means, χρώματα καὶ σχήματα and φωνή, observable in a larger
group of imitative arts.
</p>

<p>a 22
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἐν ῥυθμῷ καὶ λόγῳ καὶ ἁρμονίᾳ</lem></app>. The three terms had already 
appeared in the same sense in Plato’s analysis of the song or
choral in Rep. 398 D τὸ μέλος ἐκ τριῶν ἐστι συγκείμενον, λόγου
τε καὶ ἁρμονίας καὶ ῥυθμοῦ (comp. Laws 661c; 669p). His
terminology, however, is not always quite the same; he some-
times says ῥυθμὸς καὶ μέτρον (Phil. 17 p, Gorg. 592 6) or μέτρον
καὶ ῥυθμός (Rep. 601 a) in lieu of ῥυθμός ; and μέλος, ‘melody’ or
‘tune’, in lieu of ἁρμονία (Rep. 400 a, Gorg. 502 c, Laws 656 c,
etc.). Aristotle also, in more than one passage in the Poetics
(1, 1447 b 25; 6, 144b31), has put μέλος in place of ἁρμονία ;
and in one instance (6, 1449b29) he combines the two terms
as synonyms. It is clear, therefore, that in its present application
ἁρμονία means no more than ‘melody’ or ‘tune’. ῥυθμός is
properly ‘time’ or ‘pace’, It is a very general word, since it
includes the element of rhythm in language and in the movements
of the dance, as well as that in music; comp. Plato Laws 6654
τῇ δὴ τῆς κινήσεως τάξει [Scil. εἴπομεν ὡς] ῥυθμὸς ὄνομα εἴη, τῇ
δ᾽ αὖ τῆς φωνῆς, τοῦ τε ὀξέος ἅμα καὶ βαρέος συγκεραννυμένων,
ἁρμονία ὄνομα προσαγορεύοιτο, χορεία δὲ τὸ ξυναμφότερον κληθείη.----
672 E Ὅλη μέν που χορεία ὅλη παίδευσις ἢν ἡμῖν, τούτου δ᾽ αὖ
τὸ μὲν ῥυθμοί τε καὶ ἁρμονίαι, τὸ κατὰ τὴν φωνήν .. . τὸ δέ γε κατὰ
τὴν τοῦ σώματος κίνησιν ῥυθμὸν μὲν κοινὸν τῇ τῆς φωνῆς εἶχε
κινήσει, σχῆμα δ᾽ ἴδιον. ἐκεῖ δὲ μέλος ἡ τῆς φωνῆς κίνησις (see
also Symp. 187 Β and Phil. 17c). The various applications of
ῥυθμός are thus summarized in Aristoxenus (p. 411, 8 Marquard):
ἔστι δὲ τὰ ῥυθμιζόμενα τρία: λέξις, μέλος, κίνησις σωματική. Plato’s
view as to the great imitative capacities of rhythm and harmony
and music generally may be seen in Rep. 399 A sqq., in Laws
668 a sqq., and more briefly put, in Laws 798 D τὰ περὶ τοὺς

<pb n="104"/>

ῥυθμοὺς καὶ πᾶσαν μουσικήν ἐστι τρόπων μιμήματα βελτιόνων και
χειρόνων ἀνθρώπων. The point is recognized with equal clearness
by Aristotle in Pol. 8. 5, 1340a18, ἔστι δ᾽ ὁμοιώματα μάλιστα
παρὰ τὰς ἀληθινὰς φύσεις ἐν τοῖς ῥυθμοῖς καὶ τοῖς μέλεσιν ὀργῆς
καὶ πραότητος, ἔτι δ᾽ ἀνδρείας καὶ σωφροσύνης καὶ πάντων τῶν ἐναντίων
τούτοις καὶ τῶν ἄλλων ἠθικῶν... (a 38) ἐν δὲ τοῖς μέλεσιν αὐτοῖς
ἔστι μιμήματα τῶν ἠθῶν... (b 7) τὸν αὐτὸν γὰρ τρόπον ἔχει καὶ
τὰ περὶ τοὺς ῥυθμούς: οἱ μὲν γὰρ ἦθος ἔχουσι στασιμώτερον οἱ δὲ
κινητικόν, καὶ τούτων οἱ μὲν φορτικωτέρας ἔχουσι τὰς κινήσεις οἵ
δὲ ἐλευθεριωτέρας.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἢ χωρὶς ἢ μεμιγμένοις</lem></app> : a reminiscence of Plato Laws 669 D
διασπῶσιν οἱ ποιηταὶ ῥυθμὸν μὲν καὶ σχήματα μέλους χωρίς, λόγους
ψιλοὺς εἰς μέτρα τιθέντες, μέλος δ᾽ αὖ καὶ ῥυθμὸν ἄνευ ῥημάτων, ψιλῇ
κιθαρίσει τε καὶ αὐλήσει προσχρώμενοι.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">χρώμεναι</lem></app>, scil. ποιοῦνται τὴν μίμησιν.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τυγχάνουσιν</lem></app>. On the construction with κἂν εἰ see <bibl n="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hnjw1i&amp;seq=41">Vahlen, Beitr.
    I, p. 35</bibl>. Mr. Newman in a note on Pol. 2. 1, 1260b 31 seems to
doubt the necessity of restoring the indicative in this and other
similar places in Aristotelian texts.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἡ τῶν συρίγγων</lem></app>. The word to be supplied is apparently μίμησις---
not τέχνη, as is assumed in HSt. s.v. σῦριγξ, and in Bon. Ind.
358 39. The Platonic ἡ τῶν λόγων τέχνη in Phaedr. 260 D is not
a true parallel. For a similar genitive after μίμησις comp. Lucian
De salt. 64 ἡ μίμησις τῆς ὀρχήσεως.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">αὐτῷ δὲ τῷ ῥυθμῷ κτἑ</lem></app>. is an unnecessary clause, as ὀρχηστική is
not one of the arts in the list in a13; it will be observed too
that there is a change in the form of expression, μιμοῦνται, instead
of χρώμεναι with ποιοῦνται τὴν μίμησιν understood. The clause
would seem to have been originally an afterthought, worked in by
Aristotle as soon as he saw that there was an art that used rhythm
alone. His giving a reason for this mention of ὀρχηστική may be
supposed to imply a consciousness of its being a new point, and
one requiring demonstration.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">αἱ τῶν ὀρχηστῶν</lem></app>. The traditional reading οἱ τῶν ὀρχηστῶν has
been corrected into ἔνιοι τῶν ὀρχηστῶν by Twining ; into οἱ <add>πολλοὶ</add>
τῶν ὀρχηστῶν by Heinsius ; and into οἱ <add>χαρίεντες</add>  τῶν ὀρχηστῶν by
Zeller. It is assumed that Aristotle may have wished to recognize
the fact, of which Plato had spoken in Laws 795 Ε, that dancing
is sometimes a mere exercise of the body and without dramatic
meaning. A much simpler correction, however, is αἱ τῶν ὀρχηστῶν,
with μιμήσεις (rather than τέχναι) understood from the context.

<pb n="105"/>

Aristotle is thinking of the professional dancers, who told a story in
pantomime, by the mere movements and attitudes of their bodies
(comp. Sittl, Die Gebärden der Gr. u. Rom. p. 244).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">σχηματιζομένων ῥυθμῶν</lem></app> : the rhythms in their movements, in the
succession of their σχήματα, their gestures or attitudes (see on 26,
1462 3. 3). The emphasis is on ῥυθμῶν ; that the attitudes of the
dancer might be dramatic, and represent ‘what men do or have
done to them’, was too obvious to require saying. Aristotle is
insisting on the ‘ ethical’ significance which rhythm imparts to the
dance. On rhythm as expressive of character and temperament
see Pol. 8. 5, 1340a18 and the Platonic passages referred to
on a 22.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἤθη</lem></app> : the character and temperament of the personages represented, as distinct from their πάθη καὶ πράξεις, ‘what they do or
have done to them’. </p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">πάθη καὶ πράξεις</lem></app> : The meaning of πάθη καὶ πράξεις is suffi-
ciently shown by 9, 1451 b11 τί Ἀλκιβιάδης ἔπραξεν ἢ τί ἔπαθεν,
and 13, 1453a22 παθεῖν δεινὰ ἢ ποιῆσαι (see also On 11, 1452b 11).
πάθη is generally assumed (e.g. in Bon. Ind. 557a 49) to denote
in this passage ‘feelings’ or ‘emotions’. The words πάθη καὶ
πράξεις cover the whole ground of the story in the dance; so that
Aristotle, if he had cared to anticipate the term used later on in
6, 1450a 4, might have said here, without difference of meaning,
ἤθη καὶ μύθους.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἡ δὲ <del>ἐποποιία</del> κτἑ</lem></app>. Suckow’s correction, τυγχάνει οὖσα, is to be
found in his Form der Platonischen Schriften p. 53. With it, and
the readings implied in the Arabic Version, the whole passage
becomes intelligible and in harmony with the context. We were
told at the outset in a22 that the three means of imitation, ῥυθμός,
λόγος, and ἁρμονία, may be employed either singly or in certain
combinations. Having just spoken (1) of imitation ἐν ἁρμονίᾳ καὶ
ῥυθμῷ, and (2) of imitation ἐν ῥυθμῷ alone, Aristotle passes on
(3) to imitation ἐν λόγῳ—whether alone, or in combination with
rhythm or metre, and finally (4) to imitation ἐν ἁρμονίᾳ καὶ ῥυθμῷ
καὶ λόγῳ: This exhausts the possibilities, since it is evident that
ἁρμονία alone, and the combination ἁρμονία+λόγος, need not be
taken into account. The third of his four heads Aristotle divides,
and recognizes three possible forms of means, (1) λόγος alone,
(2) λόγος + some one kind of metre, and (3) λόγος + a plurality of
metres. In other words he distinguishes between (1) imitations in
prose, (2) imitations in some one metre (hexameters, trimeters, etc.),
and (3) imitations in a plurality of metres. Of this large and 

<pb n="106"/>
well-marked class of imitative literature, which includes the Mime, the
‘imaginary conversations’ of Socrates, the Epic, and Chaeremon’s
Centaur, Aristotle observes that it has ‘remained to this day
without a distinctive name’. The common fact here is μίμησις ἐν
λόγῳ, but there is, he says, no one common name connoting the
common fact and equally applicable to all the kinds within
the class.
</p><p>
Those who retain ἐποποιία, with the addition of ἀνώνυμος at the
end of the sentence, suppose it to mean ‘ word-poetry’ ( Wortdich-
tung, Bernays, Zwei Abhandl. p. 81). Such a special and unique
sense, however, for a term like ἐποποιία is highly improbable, and
also against the analogy of all the similar compounds (e.g. ἀρτοποιία,
μελοποιία, μυθοποιία, ὀνοματοποιία), in which the -ποιία means
simply the making of something, just as much as in ἀρτοποιία,
ὁδοποιία, παιδοποιία and the like. And even if the word could bear
its new meaning, it would be inappropriate here, as the Mime and
the ‘Socratic Conversation’ were prose imitations—not poems.
To a Greek of Aristotle’s time the idea of a prose poem would
have seemed a contradiction in terms.
a29
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τοῖς λόγοις ψιλοῖς ἢ τοῖς μέτροις</lem></app> = τοῖς λόγοις ψιλοῖς ἢ τοῖς μέτροις ψιλοῖς : comp. 2, 1448 a 11 τοὺς λόγους καὶ τὴν ψιλομετρίαν. ψιλοῖς,
which in this connexion means χωρὶς ἁρμονίας, ‘without melody’
(v. Tyrwhitt ad loc. and Bon. Ind. 433b29), differentiates this
group of imitative arts from the semi-musical arts considered
later on, at the end of the chapter; comp. Plato Phaedr. 278 C
ποίησιν ψιλὴν ἢ ἐν ὠδῇ συντέθηκε, and Laws 669 D (quoted on a 23).
λόγοις ψιλοῖς has been taken by several (including Bon. Ind.
86231) to mean ‘prose’ in the present passage—a sense which
ψιλὸς λόγος has no doubt in a good many instances, e.g. in Rhet.
3. 2, 1404b14, 33. But there is nothing in the general meaning
of the word to necessitate this interpretation here. ψιλός means
simply ‘by itself’, without some accessory, whatever the accessory
thus excluded may happen to be (v. HSt. s. v.).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἢ τοῖς μέτροις</lem></app>. μέτρα has to be understood in the concrete
sense of ‘kinds of verse’, i.e. as equivalent to λόγοι ἔμμετροι or
λόγοι + ῥυθμός. Aristotle remembers that the literary form of
imitation is generally in verse, and accordingly adds ἢ τοῖς μέτροις.
The addition, however, has a sort of reflex influence on the general
term λόγοις which precedes it, and by the contrast it suggests gives
the word for the moment the special sense of ‘ prose’, as distinct
from verse. Other instances of a general term with its meaning

<pb n="107"/>

modified by what follows will be found in 22, 1458a28 and 25, 1447a29
1460b11, The logical scheme of the statement in a 29- b23 may
be thus exhibited :—
Language without music 
    
prose

verse
in some one kind of metre
  
in a plurality of metres

Plato has the same division in Laws 810 Β, where he is protesting
against the divorce of poetry and literature from music: πρὸς δὲ
δὴ μαθήματα ἄλυρα ποιητῶν κείμενα ἐν γράμμασι, τοῖς μὲν μετὰ μέτρων
τοῖς δ᾽ ἄνευ <del>ῥυθμῶν τμημάτων <note>These two words seem to represent a gloss, ῥυθμῶν τητώμενα.</note></del>, ἃ δὴ συγγράμματα κατὰ λόγον
εἰρημένα μόνον, τητώμενα ῥυθμοῦ τε καὶ ἁρμονίας, σφαλερὰ γράμμαθ᾽
ἡμῖν ἐστι παρά τινων . . . καταλελειμμένα. Here ἄλυρα corresponds
to Aristotle’s ψιλοῖς, τοῖς μὲν μετὰ μέτρων τοῖς δ᾽ ἄνευ to his τοῖς
λόγοις ἢ τοῖς μέτροις, and κατὰ λόγον εἰρημένα μόνον τητώμενα ῥυθμοῦ
τε καὶ ἁρμονίας to his μόνον τοῖς λόγοις ψιλοῖς.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἀνώνυμος</lem></app> : Phys. 5. 2, 226 26 ἡ μὲν οὖν κατὰ τὸ ποιὸν κίνησις 
ἀλλοίωσις ἔστω· τοῦτο γὰρ ἐπέζευκται κοινὸν ὄνομα . . . ἡ δὲ κατὰ τὸ
ποσὸν τὸ μὲν κοινὸν ἀνώνυμον, καθ᾽ ἑκάτερον δ᾽ αὔξησις καὶ φθίσις.----
De anima 2. 7, 418 a 26 ὁρατὸν δ᾽ ἔστιν χρῶμά τε, καὶ ὃ λόγῳ μὲν
ἔστιν εἰπεῖν, ἀνώνυμον δὲ τυγχάνει ὄν.—H. A. 10. 40, 623 b 5 ἔστι
δέ τι γένος τῶν ἐντόμων, ὃ ἑνὶ μὲν ὀνόματι ἀνώνυμόν ἐστιν.---Pol. 3. 1,
1275 a 30 ἀνώνυμον τὸ κοινὸν ἐπὶ δικαστοῦ καὶ ἐκκλησιαστοῦ. For
other instances see Bon. Ind. 692. Aristotle has often to speak
of a class as being still without a name, because its existence has
not yet been recognized by ordinary thought (comp. Bernays, Zwei
Abhandl. p. 81).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τυγχάνει οὖσα</lem></app>. Similarly in De sensu 5, 447 7 Thurot would
restore ὑπάρχει οὖσα for ὑπάρχουσα.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ὀνομάσαι κοινὸν</lem></app> : scil. ὄνομα ; comp. Meteor. 4. 9, 387b2 οὐ γὰρ το
κεῖται ὄνομα κοινόν.---Η. A. 4. 7, 531 b 22 οὐκ ἐπέζευκται κοινὸν
ὄνομα οὐδέν.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τοὺς Σώφρονος καὶ Ξενάρχου μίμους</lem></app>. The surviving fragments
(Kaibel, CGF. 1 pp. 152 and 182) show that the mimes
of Sophron and Xenarchus were in prose (comp. Bernhardy,
Gr. Litt.3 2. 2 p. 533). And as their very name is suggestive of
μίμησις, Aristotle points to them as an indisputable example of
prose-imitation, μίμησις ἐν λόγῳ χωρὶς ἁρμονίας καὶ ῥυθμοῦ. A very
similar view of them is implied in a fr. of the dialogue περὶ
ποιητῶν (72 Teubn.): οὐκοῦν οὐδὲ ἐμμέτρους τοὺς καλουμένους
<pb n="108"/>

Σώφρονος μίμους μὴ φῶμεν εἶναι λόγους καὶ μιμήσεις, ἢ τοὺς
Ἀλεξαμενοῦ τοῦ Τηίου τοὺς πρώτους γραφέντας τῶν Σωκρατικῶν
διαλόγων (ν. Bernays, Zwei Abhandl. p. 82; Kaibel l.c., p. 152).
The fr. makes it clear that Aristotle saw a certain affinity between
the Mime and the ‘Socratic Conversations’ of Alexamenus ; and
with it before us, it is not difficult to divine the reason for the
juxtaposition of the Mime and the Σωκρατικὸς λόγος in the present
passage of the Poetics; the two things differed in name, but at
the same time they had an essential element in common, that
of being prose-imitations, μιμήσεις ἐν λόγῳ, and not (like poetry)
ἐν μέτρῳ.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">τοὺς Σωκρατικοὺς λόγους</lem></app>. As used here and in Rhet. 3. 16,
1417 a 20, the term Σωκρατικοὶ λόγοι must be taken to cover the
ground of the whole of this species of literature, the ‘Socratic
Conversations’ not only of Alexamenus, but also of Plato, Aeschines
and the rest (comp. Joel, Archiv f. Gesch. der Phil. 8, 468). A
certain resemblance between the Platonic Dialogue and the Mime
is presupposed in the story (Duris fr. 45 in Müller, FHG. 2 p. 480)
of Plato having been a zealous student and imitator of Sophron.
It is difficult, therefore, to agree with Teichmüller’s view, that
Aristotle’s intention was to contrast the Mime and the Dialogue,
and insist on the difference between them.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">οὐδὲ εἰ</lem></app>: De interpr. 11, 20b 25 οὐδὲ γὰρ ἡ ἐρώτησις μία οὐδ᾽
ἐὰν ᾖ ἀληθής.—14, 24a3 οὐδὲν διοίσει οὐδ᾽ ἂν καθόλου τιθῶμεν τὴν
κατάφασιν.---Soph. el. 11, 171b12 τὰ γὰρ ψευδογραφήματα οὐκ
ἐριστικά... οὐδέ γ᾽ εἴ τί ἐστι ψευδογράφημα περὶ ἀληθές.
</p>

<p>
At this point Aristotle runs off into a digression (comp. 9, 1451b 1)
in order to minimize the importance of the element of metre in
the imitative forms of literature. Even if a mime and a dialogue
were both written in verse, either in some one (b 11-12) or in
several kinds of metre (b 20), they would still be without a common
name connoting the μίμησις in them, which is their essential point
of agreement. The writer of such a versified mime or dialogue
might no doubt be described in ordinary parlance as an ἐποποιός
or ἐλεγειοποιός, or by some similar name indicating the kind of
verse in which his work happens to be written. Names of this
kind, however, are misleading, since they imply that the verse
rather than the μίμησις embodied in it is the essence of the
literary form of imitation. Metre, in Aristotle’s view, is only
one of the accidents of poetry; and the use of it does not make
a writer like Empedocles a poet in any true sense of the word.
</p>

<p>
<pb n="109"/>

<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἐλεγειοποιοὺς τοὺς δὲ ἐποποιοὺς</lem></app>. There is no need to understand, 
still less insert, τοὺς μὲν before ἐλεγειοποιοὺς (v. Kühner, Gr. Gr.3
2. 2 p. 265); comp. the instances cited by Vahlen (ad loc.) ; to
which may be added Soph. el. 21, 178a3, Metaph. 4. 28, 1024 a 33.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">οὐχ ὡς κατὰ τὴν μίμησιν</lem></app> = ὡς οὐ κατὰ τὴν μίμησιν. For the
position of the negative comp. Plato Phaed. 77 E ὡς δεδιότων...
πειρῶ ἀναπείθειν, μᾶλλον δὲ μὴ ὡς ἡμῶν δεδιότων, ἀλλ᾽ ἴσως ἔνι τις καὶ
ἐν ἡμῖν παῖς, ὅστις τὰ τοιαῦτα φοβεῖται.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">Ἐμπεδοκλεῖ</lem></app>. In a fragment (fr. 70 Teubn.) of the dialogue 
περὶ ποιητῶν he is declared to have been a master of all the
resources of epic language: Ὁμηρικὸς ὁ ᾿Ἐμπεδοκλῆς καὶ δεινὸς περὶ
τὴν φράσιν γέγονε, μεταφορικός τ᾽ ὢν καὶ τοῖς ἄλλοις τοῖς περὶ ποιη-
τικὴν ἐπιτεύγμασι χρώμενος. This is not inconsistent with the
present passage; Aristotle’s meaning is that, though Empedocles
may be a poet in his form, he is not a poet in his matter. A
philosophic poem comes under the head of what the ancients
termed <term>didascalice</term>, its purpose being to teach or instruct, rather
than to interest us in a μίμησις, a picture of life and manners.
That Empedocles was not in any real sense a poet is implied in
Plato Theaet. 152 Ε καὶ περὶ τούτου πάντες ἑξῆς οἱ σοφοὶ πλὴν
Παρμενίδου ξυμφερέσθων, Πρωταγόρας τε καὶ Ἡράκλειτος καὶ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς, καὶ τῶν ποιητῶν οἱ ἄκροι τῆς ποιήσεως ἑκατέρας, κωμῳδίας μὲν
Ἐπίχαρμος, τραγῳδίας δὲ Ὅμηρος--- where Empedocles, it will be
observed, is put into distinct contrast with Homer. This view of
him is more clearly stated in later writers, e.g. in Plutarch, De aud.
poet. 16 c τὰ δ᾽ Ἐμπεδοκλέους ἔπη καὶ Παρμενίδου καὶ θηριακὰ
Νικάνδρου καὶ γνωμολογίαι Θεόγνιδος λόγοι εἰσὶ κεχρημένοι παρὰ
ποιητικῆς ὥσπερ ὄχημα τὸ μέτρον καὶ τὸν ὄγκον, ἵνα τὸ πεζὸν διαφύ-
γωσιν.—Schol. Dionys. Thr. p. 166. 13 Hilgard οὐκ ἔστι ποιητὴς
ὁ μέτρῳ μόνῳ χρώμενος: οὐδὲ γὰρ Ἐμπεδοκλῆς ὁ τὰ φυσικὰ γράψας,
οὐδὲ οἱ περὶ ἀστρολογίας εἰπόντες, οὐδὲ ὁ Πύθιος ἐμμέτρως χρησμῳδῶν.
</p>

<p>b19
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ποιητὴν</lem></app>. The poet is tacitly assumed to be a μιμητὴς ἐν μέτροις 
(comp. 24, 1460a7; 25, 1460b 8).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ὁμοίως</lem></app>
 recalls the idea of the original assertion in b 9, οὐδὲν ἂν  
ἔχοιμεν ὀνομάσαι κοινὸν τοὺς Σώφρονος καὶ Ξενάρχου μίμους καὶ τοὺς
Σωκρατικοὺς λόγους. Wahlen quotes Eth. N. 1. 12, 1101 B 21 δῆλον
ὅτι τῶν ἀρίστων οὐκ ἔστιν ἔπαινος... ὁμοίως δὲ καὶ τῶν ἀγαθῶν---
where οὐκ ἔστιν ἔπαινος is to be understood. ὁμοίως often represents
the apodosis of a conditional sentence (v. An. pr. 1. 9, 30b1;
1.14, 33a 12; 1. 38, 49 a 22: De Caelo 1.4, 271a13; 42. 4,
287a19; De anima 1.1, 402 b 8). The equivalent τὸν αὐτὸν τρόπον
<pb n="110"/>

is used in just the same way in An. pr. 2. 24, 69a 11 τὸν αὐτὸν δὲ
τρόπον κἂν εἰ διὰ πλειόνων τῶν ὁμοίων ἡ πίστις γίνοιτο.

</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">Χαιρήμων</lem></app>. For the little that remains of his Κένταυρος see
Nauck, TGF.2 p. 784. Aristotle terms it a ῥαψῳδία as though it
were a sort of epic; and it is clear that in 24, 1460 a 2 he still
regards it as coming under that head. If Athenaeus 608 Ε speaks
of it as a δρᾶμα πολύμετρον, the explanation is that such a bizarre
experiment in literature might very well be placed in more than
one class. The title was no doubt taken from its subject; not
from its monstrous combination of metres, as Welcker imagines
(Nachtrag zu der Schrift iiber die Aeschylische Trilogie p. 71).
There were several comedies (Kock, CAF. 3 p. 698) and also an
ode (by Lasus of Hermione) with this or a very similar title.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">ἐξ ἁπάντων τῶν μέτρων</lem></app> : to be taken with μικτὴν (comp. Vahlen,
Aristotelische Aufsätze 2 p. 42). ἁπάντων must be an exaggera-
tion, since it is inconceivable that every kind of metre was repre-
sented in Chaeremon’s poem. Similar instances of overstatement
are to be found in b 28 (πᾶσιν), in 18, 1455 b 33 (τὸ ὅλον), in 22,
1458 a 24 (ἅπαντα), and in De anima 2. 6, 418 a 11, 19 (v. Rodier
ad loc.).
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">καὶ ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον</lem></app>
 has been altered in some apographs
into <add>οὐκ ἤδη</add> καὶ ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον and in others into καὶ
<add>τοῦτον</add> ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον. Various other corrections have
been recently suggested, e.g. κατὰ <add>τοῦτο</add> ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον
(M. Schmidt), δικαίως ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον (Ueberweg), καίτοι
ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον (Rassow and Gomperz). Susemihl omits
the clause (with Vahlen, Beitr. 1 p. 38), but finds a place for
προσαγορευτέον by inserting it after ποιητήν in b 20.
</p>

<p>
The clause (if we retain the reading of the MS.) seems to come
in in much the same way as that in b 18, διὸ τὸν μὲν ποιητὴν δίκαιον
καλεῖν, τὸν δὲ φυσιολόγον μᾶλλον ἢ ποιητήν. As an illustration
of the third of his three possibilities (comp. Vahlen, Beitr. 1 p. 4)
Aristotle cites Chaeremon’s Centaur; and his assumption is that,
as a work of this description is a μίμησις (comp. b 21 ποιοῖτο τὴν
μίμησιν) and also in verse (b 22 ἐξ ἁπάντων τῶν μέτρων), the author
is a μιμητὴς ἐν μέτροις, and therefore rightly regarded as a poet,
though popular language does not give him a special name of
the type of those considered in the preceding section (b 13-19).
The argument, therefore, will come to this: If a mime and a
dialogue were written in a medley of metres, the writers would
have to be recognized as poets; but we should have no common

<pb n="111"/>

name for the two works themselves, notwithstanding their similarity 
in form as well as nature. Some such meaning seems to be
demanded by the general logic of the argument, which is directed
to show that not only the prose forms of the literary ‘imitation’,
but also the various poetic forms of it are ‘to this day’ without
a general name (b9 ἀνώνυμος τυγχάνει οὖσα μέχρι τοῦ νῦν). The
only difficulty is to see how the clause καὶ ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον
is brought in. Vahlen (ad loc.) takes it as following after the
apodosis implied in ὁμοίως—‘adnecti non positae sed cogitatae
apodosi sententiam (καὶ ποιητὴν προσαγορευτέον). I suspect that
it was primarily meant to apply to Chaeremon, and that it is
loosely subjoined to what is said of him in the context, as an
assertion of his claim to be ranked among the poets in spite of
his metrical absurdities.
</p><p>
The question may perhaps be asked: If it was possible to give
ποιητής the sense assumed for it in this chapter and elsewhere,
why did not Aristotle recognize the word ποίημα as an equally
legitimate ‘common name’ for all the various species of verse-imitation? 
The answer may perhaps be this, that he thought
it to be (like ἐποποιός, ἐλεγειοποιός, etc.) too directly suggestive
of the metrical form (comp. Rhet. 3. 8, 1408b 30), which he puts
aside as only one of the accidents even of the poetical ‘imitation’.
</p><p>
The term ‘Poet’, as used by most of the ancients, is the subject
of a valuable inquiry by H. Weil (Études sur l’antiquité grecque,
p. 237), who shows that the nearest modern representative of
it-is ‘author’ or ‘composer’. Its primary meaning is the man
who writes the words, or composes the music, in contradistinction
to the rhapsodists, actors, singers or musicians, who present the
work to the public (comp. Plato Rep. 373 B ποιηταί τε καὶ τούτων
ὑπηρέται, ῥαψῳδοί, ὑποκριταί, χορευταί, κτἑ.). But as the literary
work which had to be thus recited or sung was by custom in
verse, the ‘poet’ was also a writer of verses. The idea of verse in
fact became part of the conventional meaning of the word—as also
of the verb ποιεῖν, which often means to write or say in verse;
the compounds, likewise, ἐποποιός, ἐλεγειοποιός, etc., all denote
writers of some kind of verse. ποιεῖν is thus opposed to λέγειν,
to speak in prose, and the ποιητής either to the συγγραφεύς, who
writes prose, or to the ἰδιώτης, the ordinary man who speaks in
prose. Another association attaching to the word had its origin
in the matter with which early Greek poetry was connected. The
poet was distinguished from the historian or chronicler by the fact

<pb n="112"/>

that he was so constantly dealing with a remote or legendary
past, in the treatment of which there was ample room for play
of imagination. All the great poetical subjects are classed by
Plato under the general head of ‘myths’ or fictions (Rep. 3774
and 382 D; comp. Xenophanes fr. 1, 21 Diels); and it was an
understood thing that a free use of fiction was one of the privileges
of the poet: Solon fr. 29 Bergk πολλὰ ψεύδονται ἀοιδοί.—Isocrates
195 D τῶν γε παλαιῶν καθόδων αὗται μάλιστ᾽ εὐδοκιμοῦσιν, ἃς παρὰ
τῶν ποιητῶν ἀκούομεν· οὗτοι γὰρ οὐ μόνον τῶν γεγενημένων τὰς
καλλίστας ἡμῖν ἀπαγγέλλουσιν, ἀλλὰ καὶ παρ᾽ αὑτῶν καινὰς συντι-
θέασιν (also Horace A. P. 9). This recognition of an element of
fiction in poetry is perhaps the nearest approach the ancients
make to our idea of ‘poetic creation’. The ordinary conception
in antiquity of the poet was that he was, just like the painter
(v. Poet. 15, 1454b9, and 25, 1460b8), an imitator, and that
his work was not so much a creation as a copy, more or less faithful,
of something already existing in legend or life.

b 25 
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">μέλει</lem></app> = ἁρμονίᾳ in the scheme in a 22.
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">μέτρῳ</lem></app>, which now takes the place of the original term λόγῳ in
a 22, has the concrete sense of ‘verse’ or versified language, i.e.
as equivalent to λόγος ἔμμετρος Or λόγος + ῥυθμός (comp. 4,
1448 b 21). It is an ill-chosen word, therefore, as it says too much,
and, if understood strictly, would make the ῥυθμῷ, with which the
enumeration begins, a superfluity.

b28 
</p>

<p>
<app><lem xml:lang="grc">αἱ μὲν ἅμα πᾶσιν αἱ δὲ κατὰ μέρος</lem></app>. As Teichmüller points
out, πᾶσιν repeats the πᾶσι in b 24, χρῶνται having to be supplied.
The antithesis is between ἅμα and κατὰ μέρος ; so that in lieu of
the latter Aristotle might have said οὐχ ἅμα ἀλλὰ κατὰ μέρος.
Comp. Meteor. 1. 14, 351 a 28 ἐκείνοις μὲν οὐ κατὰ μέρος ταῦτα
συμβαίνει πάσχειν, ἀλλ᾽ ἅμα πᾶν ἀκμάζειν καὶ φθίνειν ἀναγκαῖον.--
Plato Theaet. 189 Ε ἤτοι ἅμα γε ἢ ἐν μέρει (also Bon. Ind. 455 b 14
and 571b47). Aristotle’s language would naturally imply that,
whereas the three means of expression, language, metre, and music,
are inseparable in the Dithyramb and Nome, they appear separately
and by turns in the Drama. This, however, is an overstatement
(see on ἁπάντων in b 22), as it is only the musical element that
comes in intermittently, in the choral parts of the play (6, 1449 b 30).
</p></body></text></tei>